Finding Aid for the Book Artifacts Collection, circa 2345 B.C.-1993 A.D. (bulk circa 1510-1976)
The Bancroft Library
- Paper-making and Trade, Handmade Paper, and Machine-Made Paper, P2; ca. 1360 items
  Handmade paper samples in the collection date from the 18th century. Twentieth century samples come from several mills, notable Fabriano in Italy, John Mason’s Twelve-by-Eight mill at the College of Art in Leicester, England, and the Twinrocker Paper Mill, formerly of San Francisco, now of Brookstone, Indiana. A few undistinguished papers are retained to show imperfections caused by careless couching or faulty shakings.
  Manufactured paper samples of the Dutch firm of Van Gelder Zonen are from the collection of their customer John Henry Nash. Watermarks by A. Kolitsch of Appleton, Wisconsin, are the feature of another large group of modern samples.
  - Manual, P23E5
    - Roger Levenson, P23E5, No. 1
  - Machinery, P23M4
    - Hollander beater, P23M4, No. 1
  - Molds. Accessories, P23M6
    - Laid paper mold (without deckle); 2 samples, P23M6, No. 1
    - Wove paper mold (without deckle); 2 samples, P23M6, No. 2
    - Laid paper mold with deckle; sample, P23M6, No. 3
    - Deckle for No. 1 and No. 2, P23M6, No. 4
    - Wover paper mold without deckle, P23M6, No. 5
    - Mold for patching paper, P23M6, No. 6
    - Laid paper mold with deckle, P23M6, No. 7
    - Couching tray, P23M6, No. 8
  - Wove screens from Fourdrinier papermaking machine, P23M62
    - Watermark: "Carnation Milk", P23M62, No. 1
    - Watermark: "Memorial Bond", P23M62, No. 2
    - Watermark: unidentified building, P23M62, No. 3
    - Watermark: Great Seal of the State of California, P23M62, No. 4
    - Watermark: "A K" on shield, P23M62, No. 5
    - Section of felt from Foundrinier paper-making machine, P23M62, No. 6
  - Supplies, P23M8
    - Felts, P23M8, No. 1
    - Blotters, P23M8, No. 2
  - Paper samples: before 1800, P23S22
    - Laid paper: Holland, 1709, P23S22, No. 1
    - Laid paper: Holland, 1787, P23S22, No. 2
  - Paper samples: 1800-to-date, P23S23
    - De Luxe Handmade Papers. Bergisch Gladbach, Germany: J.W. Zanders, P23S23, No. 1
    - Wove handmade, P23S23, No. 2
    - Tovil laid handmade. Maidstond, England: Barcham Green, P23S23, No. 3
    - Laid handmade. Maidstone, England: Barcham Green, P23S23, No. 4
    - Laid handmade. Maidstone, England: Barcham Green, P23S23, No. 5
    - Wove rag (machine made) ledger bond: early 19th C., P23S23, No. 6
    - Japanese mending paper (2 pieces), P23S23, No. 7
    - Wove handmade, with unbeaten fibers added. San Francisco: Twinrocker Paper Mill, 1971-72 (Howard and Katherine Clark), P23S23, No. 8
    - Wove (machine made): Strathmore text, P23S23, No. 9
    - Laid (machine made): Curtis Tweedweave text, P23S23, No. 10
    - Magnolia Editions Stock paper. --Oakland, Calif.: "Magnolia Editions", P23S23, No. 11
    - "Making Paper from Mitnan" / by Joyce Schmidt and Meyer Bar-Ad. --Beer-Sheva, Israel: Visual Art Centre, 1980?, P23S23, No. 12
    - Straw paper keepsake / by Joseph E. Brown. --Rochester, N.Y.: Rochester Institute of Technology, 1980, P23S23, No. 13
    - Tissue for the conservation and book arts trade / by Timothy D. Barrett.--Kalamazoo, Michigan: Kalamazoo Handmade Papers, 1980?, P23S23, No. 14
    - "Making Paper by Hand in Korea" / by Yeong-Yon Kim. --Seoul, Korea: 1980, P23S23, No. 15
    - Price lists from Asao Shimura.--Ibaragi-Ken, Japan: Cannabis pressm 1980 [?], P23S23, No.16
    - Sample papers / by Elaine Koretsky.--Carriage house Handmade Paper Works, 1980 [?], P23S23, No. 17
  - Paper samples: dealers' booklets, P23S24
    - European and Oriental Printing, Art and Parchment Papers. Andrews/Nelson/Whitehead, P23S24, No. 1
    - 3M Printing and Art Papers. Andrews/Nelson/Whitehead, P23S24, No. 2
    - Hakone Colored Tissue. Andrews/Nelson/Whitehead, P23S24, No. 3
    - Oriental Printing and Art Paper. Andrews/Nelson/Whitehead, P23S24, No. 4
    - Fabriano Cover. Andrews/Nelson/Whitehead, P23S24, No. 5
  - Paper samples: John Mason's Twelve by Eight Mill, P23S25
    - Wove rag writing paper. Watermark: "John Mason" portrait in vignette, P23S25, No. 1
    - Wove rag writing paper with a leaf integral with the sheet, P23S25, No. 2
    - Wove paper with two leaves integral with the sheet, P23S25, No. 3
    - Wove experimental printing papers, formed from man-made or synthetic fibers, P23S25, No. 4-14
  - Paper samples: Van Gelder Zonen, P23S28
    - Booklets, P23S281
    - Stationary in various sizes, P23S282
    - Full size sheets, P23S283
  - Paper samples: watermarks (Countermarks not differentiated), P23W2
    - "John Henry Nash" (2), "VGZ" (2), Unicorn (2), in laid paper, P23W2, No. 1
    - "VGZ" (2) "Hearst", "Nash", Unicorns (2), in laid paper, P23W2, No. 2
    - "VGZ", Unicorn, in laid paper, P23W2, No. 3
    - "JHN" (2), Unicorns (2) in laid paper, P23W2, No. 4
    - "1885 Stork All linen" is a single sheet of all linen, P23W2, No. 5
    - "John Henry Nash San Francisco," Greek fret in wove bond, P23W2, No. 6a-6c
    - "JHN", "John Henry Nash" in laid bond, P23W2, No. 7a-7d
    - "John Henry Nash" (2), "VGZ" (2), Unicorn (2), in laid paper, P23W2, No. 8
    - "Libby Owens Ford Trademark" in wove tissue, P23W2, No. 9
    - Wood grain (2), Free form (2), in wove paper, P23W2, No. 10
    - "International Brotherhood of Papermarks 241 Made" in wove paper, P23W2, No. 11
    - Watermaking Dandy Rolls "Progress Jos.J.Plank & Co. Appleton Wis" Scene in light and shade technique in wove paper, P23W2, No. 12
    - "R.L.R. Professional Parchment Rag Content" in wove bond, P23W2, No. 13
    - "Lions International" logo in cockled wove bond, P23W2, No. 14
    - "Voucher Bond A Butler Paper Rag Content", in wove bond, P23W2, No. 15
    - "CSC", in wove bond, P23W2, No. 16
    - "Shlitz Beer Trademark", in wove bond, P23W2, No. 17
    - "CO-OP" in cockled wove bond, P23W2, No. 18
    - "Parchment Script" in wove bond in folio, P23W2, No. 19
    - "Wausautone", in lightweight yellow wove cover stock, P23W2, No. 20
    - "Airdale Bond Rag Content", in cockled wove bond, P23W2, No. 21
    - "Minute man Letter Rag Content", Minute man in vignette with check pattern in wove bond, P23W2, No. 22a
    - "Minute Man Letter Rag Content", Minute man in outline with check pattern wove bond, P23W2, No. 22b
    - Minute man with check pattern in wove board, P23W2, No. 22c
    - "Tesoro Nacional de Bolivia Papel Valorado", with coat of arms in white wove bond, P23W2, No. 23
    - "Man of the Hour General MacArthur N JIP", Profile in light and shade in white wove text paper, P23W2, No. 24
    - "Nation Wide Mimeo" in green wove mimeograph paper, P23W2, No. 25
    - "Nation Wide Mimeo" in buff wove mimeograph paper, P23W2, No. 26
    - "Nation Wide Mimeo" in white wove mimeograph paper, P23W2, No. 27
    - "Montags Extra 100 Rag" in striped pattern blue bond, P23W2, No. 28
    - "Jos.J.Plank & Co. Appleton Wisconsin", in blue wove-paper, P23W2, No. 29a
    - "Jos.J.Plank & Co. Appletone Wisconsin", in think blue wove-paper, P23W2, No. 29b
    - House and cloud scend in light-and-shade in buff wove-paper, P23W2, No. 30
    - "Hand Made in USA" in grey laid bond, P23W2, No. 31
    - Galleon in shadow in white wove bond, P23W2, No. 32
    - "Greetings from Appleton" in airplane in cream wove bond, P23W2, No. 33
    - "Made with hand mold" in laid sheet, P23W2, No. 34
    - "Jos.J.Plank & Co. Appleton, Wisconsin". Three Wise Men in light-and-shade, in folded Christmas card, pebble-finished text paper. "A Merry Christmas Happy New Year 1940" in Christmas tree cut out fold, P23W2, No. 35
    - "Mr. & Mrs. A. Kolitsch Appleton WIs." in grey patterned bond, P23W2, No. 36
    - "Made with hand mould by A.K. in Appleton" in gray bond, P23W2, No. 37
    - "A. Kolitsch, Appleton Wis" in lined gray bond, P23W2, No. 38
    - Waves in striped ivory bond, P23W2, No. 39
    - Herald in laid bond, P23W2, No. 40
    - "The best papers are made from rags", set within triangle reading, "Use better papers for durability and impressiveness", in gray wove-bond, P23W2, No. 41
    - "American Legion", logo in beige wove-bond, P23W2, No. 42
    - "Republica El Salvador en La America Central", coat of arms in white wove-bond, P23W2, No. 43
    - "Republica Argentine Ley de Selios", coat of arms (2) in gray wove bond, P23W2, No. 44
    - "Lincoln Letter". Lincoln in vignette on cream wove-bond, P23W2, No. 45
    - "Made with hand mold" in gray laid bond with diagonal chain lines, P23W2, No. 46
    - "Spend Your Vacation in Wisconsin Land O'Lakes with map of state in buff wove-bond, P23W2, No. 47
    - Wood textured watermark in ivory bond cut to fold into envelope, P23W2, No. 48
    - Flower textured watermark in ivory bond cut to fold into envelope, P23W2, No. 49
    - "Peace on Earth Good Will to Men" with manger scene and soldier and sailor in relief in ivory wove-bond, P23W2, No. 50
    - "US 1941" in blue bond No. 10 envelope, P23W2, No. 51
    - "US 1945" in white bond No. 10 envelope, P23W2, No. 52
    - "US 1929" in white bond No. 10 envelope, P23W2, No. 53
    - "Clover linen bond" with bird in light and shate in pink wove-bond, P23W2, No. 54
- Practical Printing, Pressroom and Composing Room Equipment, P7
  The Press Room of The Bancroft Library was established to provide for the demonstrations and teaching of the principles of hand printing. Most of the tools, type and other equipment recorded in this section are in the room and available for immediate use.
  Important type faces at hand include: Arrighi, Baskerville roman, Bodoni roman and italic, Cloister Old Style roman, italic and small capitals, Cloister Lightface roman, italic and small capitals, Oxford roman and italic, Union Pearl, and F.W. Goudy’s Berkeley Old Style.
  Type is stored in California Job Cases, Yankee Job Cases, Double-Yankee Job Cases and upper and lower cases that came from Jeff Craemer and from the Merrymount Press of Daniel B. Updike, the Arundo Press of Frederick Folger Thomas, Jr., and the University of California Printing Department.
  When the printer starts work, his first task is to set type in a composing stick. Then he moves the assembled type to a galley, an open-ended metal storage tray in which he makes up one page, which he ultimately transfers to a chase that holds all of the pages to be printed at one time. He fills the blank spaces in the chase with metal or wooden furniture, the latter selected from the complete font in its special cabinet given by Jeff Craemer. Finally he locks the whole in place with quoins. Throughout the entire process he has access to the Press Room to a large assortment of composing-room and general tools.
  Early Printers often made corrections at various times during a press run. This practice resulted, especially during the 17th century, in important works with textual differences that still baffle scholars. A half-scale replica of an English wooden press was built in 1976 by Richard Hicks according to Joseph Moxon’s description in Mechanick Exercises (London 1685). Since the form is twice the area of the platen, a full-size sheet is printed by two pulls of the bar. The ink block holds four ink balls; the chase is accompanied by a special hook, brass shooting stick, wooden mallet, platen bearers, press points, and quoins, all the gift of Roger Levenson.
  The Berkeley Albion Press is a Super-Royal Albion handpress made in London before 1856 S & T Sharwood. It has its own special chases and ink roller; printing is accomplished by pulling a level called the toggle which moves the platen into the form. This press is also the gift of Roger Levenson, who purchased it in 1953 from Leonard Hyman, an English dealer in rare music and rare music books. Previously it had been rehabilitated to appear in an English motion picture.
  An American press built on the same general principle is the Reliance, a Washington-style handpress purchased many years ago from Jane Grabhorn by James D. Hart for personal use in his home. On his death, it came to The Bancroft Library.
  A table-model Royal Octavo Albion handpress bearing the service plate of Hughes & Kimber, Ltd. Of Longon is named the Valenti Angelo Press for its last owner. Earlier owners were Emery Walker, Bruce Rogers and John Fass (Hammer Creek Press). Midway in size between the Berkeley Albion and the Valenti Angelo Press is a third Albion, a “crown broadside” press, made in London by H. W. Caslon in 1861. It formerly belonged to the School of Library and Information Science, where it was part of the equipment of the old South Hall Press.
  Small jobbing, or platen, presses that reproduce the entire printing surface at one pull are an Exclesior Platen Job Press, a gift of John Barr Tompkins, a side-lever platen job press from the Beulah Mitchell Clute Collection, the gift of Mrs. Herbert Blasdale, and a Chandler and Price Pilot Press, the gift of Mrs. Frederick Folger Thomas, Jr., who also donated the Nolan Proof Press.
  Most of the presses in the Bancroft collection print from raised letters, or are, in other words, letterpress. Intaglio, or printing from a plate that has been etched or engraved, the lines filled with ink and then wiped clean, may be done on the small etching press manufactured by N. N. Kelton in New York City during the 1890s. It could also be used to produce embossed cards. The press was given by Karl Kasten, Professor Emeritus of Art, on behalf of the California Printmakers Society.
  - Brackets, P7B7
    - Set of iron brackets for upper and lower case, P7B7, No. 1
  - Case cabinets and case stands, P7C2
    - Oak case stand: standard size, P7C2, No. 1
    - Oak case cabinet: standard size, stained black, P7C2, No. 2
    - Oak bookbinder's dust-proof type cabinet. Two Rivers, Wisc: Hamilton, P7C2, No. 3
    - Oak dust-proof case cabinet. Two Rivers, Wisc.: Hamilton, P7C2, No. 4
    - Oak foundry-type cabinet, P7C2, No., 5
    - Oak case cabinet, P7C2, No. 6
    - Oak case stand, P7C2, No. 7
    - Oak case cabinet: two-thirds size. Ludington, Mich.: The Tubbs Mfg. Co., P7C2, No. 8
  - Type Storage: Cases, P7C23
    - Upper case, P7C23, No. 1
    - Upper case, P7C23, No. 2
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 3
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 4
    - Upper case, P7C23, No. 5
    - Standard lower case, P7C23, No. 6
    - Standard lower case, P7C23, No. 7
    - Standard Upper case, P7C23, No. 8
    - Standard lower case, P7C23, No. 9
    - Upper case, P7C23, No. 10
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 11
    - Upper case, P7C23, No. 12
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 13
    - Upper case, P7C23, No. 14
    - Upper case, P7C23, No. 15
    - Blank case, P7C23, No. 16
    - Blank case, P7C23, No. 17
    - Upper case, P7C23, No. 18
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 19
    - Upper case, P7C23, No. 20
    - Upper case, P7C23, No. 21
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 22
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 23
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 24
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 25
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 26
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 27
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 28
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 29
    - Blank case, P7C23, No. 30
    - Double Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 34
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 35
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 36
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 37
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 38
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 39
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 40
    - Upper case, P7C23, No. 41
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 42
    - Upper case, P7C23, No. 43
    - Upper case, P7C23, No. 44
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 45
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 46
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 47
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 48
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 49
    - Blank case, P7C23, No. 50
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 51
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 52
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 53
    - Triple Capital case, P7C23, No. 54
    - Triple Capital case, P7C23, No. 55
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 56
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 57
    - Triple Capital case, P7C23, No. 58
    - Upper case, P7C23, No. 59
    - Upper case, P7C23, No. 60
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 61
    - Blank case, P7C23, No. 62
    - Blank case, P7C23, No. 63
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 64
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 65
    - Double Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 66
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 67
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 68
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 69
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 70
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 71
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 72
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 73
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 74
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 75
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 76
    - Lower case, P7C23, No. 77
    - Quadruple Capital case, P7C23, No. 78
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 79
    - California Job case, P7C23, No. 80
    - Two-thirds accent case, P7C23, No. 81
    - Two-thirds upper case, P7C23, No. 82
    - Quarter sorts case, P7C23, No. 83
    - Two-thirds accent case, P7C23, No. 84
    - Space case, P7C23, No. 85
    - Space case, P7C23, No. 86
    - Space case, P7C23, No. 87
    - Space box with handle, P7C23, No. 88
    - Bookbinder's one-half capital case, P7C23, No. 89
    - Bookbinder's one-half capital case, P7C23, No. 90
    - Bookbinder's one-half capital case, P7C23, No. 91
    - Bookbinder's one-half capital case, P7C23, No. 92
    - Bookbinder's one-half capital case, P7C23, No. 93
    - Bookbinder's one-half capital case, P7C23, No. 94
    - Bookbinder's one-half capital case, P7C23, No. 95
    - Bookbinder's one-half capital case, P7C23, No. 96
    - Bookbinder's one-half capital case, P7C23, No. 97
    - Bookbinder's one-half capital case, P7C23, No. 98
    - Space case, P7C23, No. 99
    - Lead and slug case, P7C23, No. 100
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 101
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 102
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 103
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 104
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 105
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 106
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 107
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 108
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 109
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 110
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 111
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 112
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 113
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 114
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 115
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 116
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 117
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 118
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 119
    - Yankee Job case, P7C23, No. 120
  - Chases, P7C4
    - Chase (No. 197570), P7C4, No. 1
    - Chase, P7C4, No. 2
    - Chase, P7C4, No. 3
    - Chase (No. 236880), P7C4, No. 4
    - Chase (No. 228), P7C4, No. 5
    - Chase (No. 228), P7C4, No. 6
    - Chase (No. 39002): with two cross-bars and two rollers, P7C4, No. 7
    - Chase: in four places, P7C4, No. 8
    - Chase: 17th C. replica. Cedar Crest, New Mexico: Richard Hicks, 1976, P7C4, No. 9
    - Chase, P7C4, No. 10
    - Chase, P7C4, No. 11
  - Page frames, P7F2
    - 30 picas. Chicago: Rouse, 1923, P7F2, No. 1a-1d
    - 20 Picas. Chicago: Rouse, 1923, P7F2, No. 2a-2d
  - Furniture, wood, P7F3
    - Small font (i.e. 280 pieces), P7F3, No. 10.1-60.34
    - Furniture cabinet, P7F31, No. 1
  - Furniture, metal, P7F4
    - Cast iron, P7F4, No. 1
    - Cast lead alloy, P7F4, No. 2
  - [Platen bearers], P7F5
    - Platen bearers (17th C. replicas), P7F5, No. 1-2
  - [Wedges], P7F6
    - Wedges (17th C. replicas), P7F6, No. 1-8
  - Furnishings: tables, cabinets, P7F8
    - Oak filing cabinet, P7F8, No. 1
    - Oak broadside case: two-door front, inside storage, P7F8, No. 2
    - Oak broadside case: 7 drawers (101 cm. ea.), 8 drawers (80 cm. ea.), P7F8, No. 3
    - Work table with 3 shelves, P7F8, No. 4
    - Typing table with drawer, P7F8, No. 5
  - [Galleys and Galley Cabinet], P7G2
    - Galleys, P7G2, No. 1-60
    - Galley cabinet, P7G21, No. 1
  - Ink and inking equipment, P7I6
    - Roller for the Berkeley Albion Press, P7I6, No. 1
    - Ink: Janecke-Schneeman, 1951, P7I6, No. 2
    - Catalog: Janecke-Schneeman, 1955, P7I6, No. 3
    - Ink block (17th C. Replica), P7I6, No. 4
    - Ink balls (17th C. replica), P7I6, No. 5-8
  - Presses, P7P7
    - Bobcat press (17th C. replica), P7P7, No. 1
    - Berkeley Albion Press (Super-Royal Albion), P7P7, No. 2
    - Valenti Angelo Press (Royal Octavo Albion), P7P7, No. 3
    - Nolan Proof Press, P7P7, No. 4
    - Chandler and Price Pilot Platen Job Press, P7P7, No. 5
    - Kelsey "Excelsior" Platen Job Press, P7P7, No. 6
    - Benjamin Franklin's press (wooden model), P7P7, No. 7
    - Beulah Mitchell Clute Platen Job Press, P7P7, No. 8
    - James D. Hart's Reliance Press, P7P7, No. 9
    - Engraver's and Etcher's Rolling Press, P7P7, No. 10
    - Crown Broadside Albion Press, P7P7, No. 11
  - General tools, P73T6
    - [Miscellaneous printing tools], P73T6, No. 1-52
      Awls, braces, bits, screw drivers bits, capenter's square, T-square, C clamp, cold chisel, compass, file, rasp, hammer, card cutter, etc.
  - Composing room tools, P73T7
    - [Miscellaneous composing room tools], P73T7, No. 1-81
  - Printing types, P73T9
    - [Over 100 Different Types Faces and Sizes of Fonts], P73T9
- Office Equipment, Q2
  The office equipment portion of the collection includes typewriters, word processors, and computing equipment such as a laptop and desktop computer.
  - Typewriters, Q2B2
    - Remington manual, Q2B2, No. 1
    - IBM Selectric, Q2B2, No. 2
  - Computers, Q2C3
    - Apple IIe, Q2C3, No. 1
    - Macintosh Powerbook 180c
  - Computer software manuals, Q2C34
    - [Miscellaneous software manuels], Q2C34
    - Mimeograph Machines, Q2D1
    - Rotary Neostyle No. 8-F Mimoegraph, The Neostyle Company, New York, ca. 1910.; Q2D1 No. 1; 15" square at the base, 16" tall and weighs 29 lbs.
      Gift of John Brandi, November 2013 as an addition to the John Brandi papers (BANC MSS 2009/112). Identical to the model which Brandi used to print his early Nail / Tooth of Time books, copies of which are owned by the Bancroft Library.
- Typography, T8
  An historical figure sometimes credited with the invention of the movable type is Pi Sheng, a Chinese man who lived about 1041 A.D. and is said to have used characters carved in moistened clay. Recently a professional potter and amateur printer, Paul Quyle, set himself the task of producing a satisfactory clay type. He has given the library a piece of his experimental type and a printed copy of his summary of the problems involved. He concluded that not even the exquisite craftsmanship of the Chinese would have been equal to the challenge.
  Historians of printing do not know the exact nature of typecasting equipment used by the first Western printers. Since the early 1700’s the standard hand-mold has been similar to the one used by William Caslon and given by his great grandson to John Henry Nash. It is constructed to hold a matrix struck with a punch carrying the design of the character to be cast.
  The preparation of a punch can be explained with a display that shows each step from raw material to finished punches selected from the John Henry Nash Collection. The counterpunches, which produce the hollows in letterforms, were cut by R. Hunter Middleton to match the Nash punches. Related items that can be handled are a handcut punch from the 19th century France, a handcut counterpunch, and a matrix for a handmold.
  Historical type specimens include three pieces of Korean movable type of the 15th century, the gift of Dr. and Mrs. John Barr Tompkins, and a specimen of type cast by the Oxford University type foundry from matrices given to Oxford in 1686 by John Fell.